Guide to the Barbara Kopple: Peekskill Riots Collection TAM 307
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Barbara Kopple: Peekskill Riots Papers
Bulk, 1949-1981
1925-1999, (Bulk 1949-1981)
TAM 307
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
5.0 linear feet (6 boxes)
Assembled by filmmaker Barbara Kopple in preparation for two feature-length films, the collection documents two Paul Robeson concerts in August and September of 1949 to benefit the Civil Rights Congress and the anti-Communist/anti-radical riots by civilians that took place in reaction to the concerts (preventing the first one from actually taking place). The collection includes administrative files related to the film projects; scripts; subject files, clippings and correspondence; and a small number of artifacts and ephemera related to the riots.
Kopple, Barbara.
Provenance
The Barbara Kopple: Peekskill Riots Collection was given to the Tamiment Library at New York University by Barbara Kopple in April 2004. A final version of "Joe Glory" and an article on Paul Robeson's legacy were donated by Jeffrey Stanley in 2009.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
In July 1949, the Harlem chapter of the Civil Rights Congress announced that Paul Robeson would headline a benefit concert for the organization in Lakeland Acres, near Peekskill, New York. Local organizations, including the Junior Chamber of Commerce, and the local newspaper, The Peekskill Evening Star, condemned the concert as Communist-inspired and encouraged demonstrations to stop it. The resulting local opposition grew out of potent elements of anti-Communist, anti-black and anti-Semitic sentiment present in the post-World War II United States.
On August 27th, the day the concert was scheduled to take place, a mob of locals attacked arriving concertgoers with billy clubs, brass knuckles and rocks, overturning cars and burning political handouts and pamphlets. Local police stood by, and intervened only after thirteen people were seriously injured. As a result, Robeson never made it to the concert site, and the concert never took place.
Deeply angered by this incident, the Civil Rights Congress held a large public meeting at Harlem’s Golden Gate Ballroom and declared that the concert would be rescheduled for September 4th.
Located on the grounds of the Hollow Brook Golf Course in Cortlandt Manor, this concert drew twenty thousand people. Security was provided by trade unionists, including members of District Council 65, and Robeson and other musicians, including Pete Seeger, were able to perform. Once the concert ended, however, attendees were forced to run a gauntlet of veterans and outside agitators who threw rocks through the windshields of their cars and buses. At least 140 people were injured and numerous vehicles were severely damaged.
Widespread outrage ensued as a result of this violence, and over three hundred people went to Albany to meet with Governor Thomas E. Dewey. Governor Dewey would not give them a hearing, and instead blamed the events on the provocation of “communist groups.” A $2 million civil suit was filed by Robeson and twenty-six other plaintiffs against Westchester County and two veterans’ groups. The case was dismissed after three years of litigation.
This collection of material related to the Peekskill Riots was created by Barbara Kopple, a director known for films such as Harlan County U.S.A.(1976), American Dream(1990) and Shut Up & Sing(2006), in connection with two proposed film projects on the Peekskill Riots. In 1979 Koppel began, in conjunction with screenwriter Loring Mandel, to develop a feature-length drama, tentatively titled “Peekskill,” and partially funded by Twentieth Century Fox. The bulk of the research collection seems to have been created at this time. This project appears to have been abandoned sometime after 1980 as a result of contract disputes with Mandel and lack of funding.
Sources:
American Civil Liberties Union. Violence in Peekskill: A Report of the Violations of Civil Liberties at Two Paul Robeson Concerts Near Peekskill, N.Y., August 27th and September 4th, 1949. New York: ACLU, 1949.
Fast, Howard. Peekskill, USA: Inside the Infamous 1949 Riots. Mineola: Dover Publications, 2006.
The Robeson Concerts: Peekskill, NY 1949. Dir. Abby Luby. Videocassette. ORB Total Media, 1998.
Walwick, Joseph. The Peekskill, New York, Anti-Communist Riots of 1949. Lewiston: Edwin Mellen Press, 2002.
Scope and Content Note
Series I, Administrative Files, 1979-1999, consists largely of correspondence, contracts and expense reports relating to "Peekskill," a documentary based on the Peekskill Riots and surrounding events and "Joe Glory," a docudrama with fictional characters set against the backdrop of the Peekskill Riots.
Series II, Scripts, 1979-1984. Various versions of scripts for “Peekskill” and “Joe Glory” are included in this series, as well as a story treatment of the Peekskill Riots by Pete Seeger entitled, “Auntie Rosa’s Victory.”
Series III, Subject Files and Clippings, 1925-1981, contains the bulk of the collection and includes a large number of original clippings from newspapers such as the Peekskill Evening Star, the Daily Compass, the Daily Worker and New York City newspapers such as the Post, Mirror, Times, and News.
Of particular significance are original records from the office of George Fanelli, the Westchester County District Attorney who was charged with investigating the riots. Original reports and correspondence from the New York State Police and the Westchester County Sherriff’s Office are also noteworthy.
Also included are letters to the editor of the Peekskill Evening Star, which had condemned the Robeson concerts and called for counter-demonstrations. From correspondents spread across the United States, these letters express a range of sentiments regarding the Robeson concert and the ensuing violence, and supply a window into citizens’ views of Communism, race and other social issues in post-World War II America.
A portion of the research material, including scholarly articles and notes on primary sources, was collected between 1970 and 1973 by Malcolm Call, then a Ph.D. candidate at the University of Massachusetts, in preparation for his dissertation proposal, "The Cold War at Home: Peekskill, NY, 1949." This material was apparently later acquired by Kopple and integrated into her research collection. Kopple’s own notes, including lists of and material provided by potential interviews are also included.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series.
Organized into 4 series: I. Administrative Files, 1979-1999 II. Scripts, 1979-1984 III. Subject Files and Clippings, 1925-1981 IV. Artifacts, Ephemera and Oversize Clippings, 1936-1949
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Barbara Kopple: Peekskill Riots Oral History Collection (Oral History #2.4)
Barbara Kopple: Peekskill Riots Photographs (Photos #228)
Communist Party of the USA Photographs (Photographs #223)
Communist Party of the USA Records: Paul Robeson Clippings and Ephemera (Tamiment #132.09)
Westchester Committee for a Fair Inquiry into the Peekskill Riots (Tamiment Vertical File)
American Civil Liberties Union.; American Jewish Committee.; American Legion.; Call, Malcolm L.; Civil Rights Congress (U.S.).; Fanelli, George M.; Fast, Howard, 1914-2003.; Kopple, Barbara.; New York State Police.; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976.; Seeger, Pete, 1919-; Anti-communist movements |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century.; Antisemitism |z New York (State) |z New York.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Official reports.; Peekskill (N.Y.); Peekskill (N.Y.) |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Peekskill (N.Y.) |x Race relations; Racism |z New York (State) |z Peekskill; Research notes.; Riots |z New York (State) |z Peekskill; Screenplays.
- Series I: Administrative Files, 1979-1999.
  - Bonded Services Film Storage: Correspondence and Inventory, 1989-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Buchthal, Stanley "Bucky" (attorney), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Contracts: ABC News Broadcast Agreement, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Contracts: Buckeye Entertainment (Director’s Agreement), 1980, 1983, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Contracts: Director Borrowing Agreement, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Contracts: Mandel, Loring (screenwriter) Deal Memo, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Contracts: Mohegan Film Productions and Pantheon Pictures, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Contracts: Slote, Al (screenwriter) Agreement, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Contracts: Twentieth Century Fox Deal Memo, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1980, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Expenses, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Freedom of Information Act Files, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Legal, 1979-1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Expense Reports, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Legal (Buchthal): "Joe Glory", 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mohegan Film Productions, Inc: Certificate of Incorporation, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Resource Information and Phone Numbers, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Screenwriters: Correspondence and Resumes, 1979-1980, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Staff Meeting Agendas, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Staff: Resumes (project employees), undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Series II: Scripts, 1979-1984.
  - "Auntie Rosa's Victory": Script Sketch by Pete Seeger (edited typescript), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Joe Glory": Final Draft, Jan 1998 (Box 1, Folder 21a)
  - "Joe Glory": Reader’s Report, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Joe Glory": Script (74 pp, revised by Jeffrey Stanley), undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Joe Glory": Script (123 pp), undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Joe Glory": Script (118 pp), undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Joe Glory": Script (139 pp), undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Joe Glory": Script Comments, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Joe Glory": Script Fragment, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Mandel, Loring (screenwriter): Research Materials and Notes, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Peekskill": Character and Plot Development, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "Peekskill": Script (I), undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Peekskill": Script (II), undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Peekskill": Script Fragments (pp 1-47), undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Peekskill": Script Notes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "Peekskill": Script Revisions, Jun 1980 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Peekskill": Story Treatment, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Peekskill Film Project: Script Development Funding Proposal, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "Peekskill USA": Book Proposal, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Series III: Subject Files and Clippings, 1925-1981.
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - American Jewish Committee: "Report on Activities in Peekskill, New York", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - American Legion, undated, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Anti-Defamation League of B’nai B’rith, 1949-1972 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Articles: General, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Articles: Jewish Life(photocopies), 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Benson, Mildred, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bibliographical Sources, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bland, Robert O. (Concert Organizer): Telephone Call Logs, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Call, Malcolm L.: Correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Call, Malcolm L.: Research Files, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Call, Malcolm L.: "The Cold War at Home: Peekskill, NY, 1949" (Ph.D. dissertation proposal, University of Massachusetts), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Card File: Contacts and Information, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Catholic War Veterans, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Civil Rights Congress, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Clergy Statement on Peekskill Riots, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Clippings: Adler-Draper Case, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Clippings: Amerasia Case, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Clippings: American Civil Liberties Union, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Clippings and Notes, Oct 1948-Jul 1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Clippings and Notes, Aug 1949 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Clippings and Notes, Sep 1, 1949-Sep 10, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Clippings and Notes, Sep 11, 1949-Sep 29, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Clippings and Notes, Oct 1, 1949-Dec 25, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Clippings and Notes, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Clippings and Notes: Peekskill Evening Star, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Clippings and Notes: Paul Robeson, 1945-1956 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Clippings: Baltimore Afro-American, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Clippings: Bittleman, Alexander, 1950, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Clippings: Bridges, Harry, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Clippings: Brothman, Abraham, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Clippings: Budenz, Louis (Communism in Westchester County), 1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: Christian Science Monitor, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Clippings: Communism, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Clippings: Communism (editorials), 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Clippings: Coplon, Judith and Valentin A. Gubitcher, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Clippings: Cvetic, Matthew, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Clippings: Daily Compass, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Clippings: Daily Worker, Aug 1949 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Clippings: Daily Worker, Sep 1949 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Clippings: Feinberg Law, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Clippings: Field, Frederick Vanderbilt, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Clippings: Film Project, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Clippings: General, 1946-1950, 1971, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Clippings: Hiss, Alger, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Clippings: Index to Clipping Files, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Clippings: Indian Point, 1946-1955, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Clippings: International Workers Order, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Clippings: Marxist-Jefferson School, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Clippings: Massing, Hede, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Clippings: National Guardian, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Clippings: New York Daily Mirror, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Clippings: New York Daily News, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Clippings: New York Herald Tribune, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Clippings: New York Journal American, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Clippings: New York Post, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Clippings: New York Star, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Clippings: New York Times, 1949-1950, 1970, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Clippings: New York World-Telegram, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Clippings: Peekskill (town), 1949, 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Clippings: Peekskill Evening Star, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Clippings: Pittsburgh Courier, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Clippings: Pressman, Lee, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Clippings: Putnam County News and Reporter, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Clippings: Remington, William W., 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Clippings: The Reporter Dispatch (White Plains), 1949 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Clippings: Robeson, Paul, 1972-1979 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Clippings: Rogge, O. John, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Clippings: Schultz, Rabbi Benjamin (American Jewish League against Communism), 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Communism: General, undated, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Concert Program, Sep 4, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence: Contemporary Comment, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Co-operative League, 1933-1936 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Fanelli, George (Westchester County District Attorney): Letters to, Aug 1949-Sep 1949 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Fanelli, George: Notes from Grand Jury Investigation, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Fanelli, George: Report to Governor Thomas E. Dewey, Sep 1949 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Fanelli, George: Telegrams, Aug 1949-Sep 1949 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Fascist Organizations, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Fine, David (concert attendee), 1949-1979 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Gold, Herman, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Goldsand, Ronald: "Peaceful Is Better but Violence Is Okay Too" (typescript), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Grand Jury: Charges and Witnesses, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Grand Jury: Exhibits, Aug 1949 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Grand Jury: Report, Oct 1949 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Grand Jury: Subpoenas, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Grand Jury: Testimonies, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Grand Jury: Witness Legend, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Grand Jury: Witnesses, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Greenberg, Kenneth: "Anti-Communism in Harlem During the 1940's" (typescript), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Hearings Regarding Communist Infiltration of Minority Groups, Part I (HUAC - includes testimony from Benjamin Schultz, Jackie Robinson), Jul 1949 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Hollowbrook Lake Association, 1949-1953 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Kaufman, Maurice (concert organizer), 1949, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Labor Unions, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - McAuliffe, Mary S.: "The Politics of Civil Liberties: The ACLU During the McCarthy Years" (typescript), undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Neuburger, Shapiro, Rabinowitz and Boudin (attorneys): Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - New York State Police: Arrest Report, Sep 1949 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - New York State Police: Correspondence, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - New York State Police: Investigation and Reports, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Oral Histories: Correspondence, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Oral Histories: Interview Notes and Summaries, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Oral Histories: Interviewee Lists, 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Peekskill: History, 1949-1979 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Peekskill Evening Star: Letters to the Editor, Aug 1949 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Peekskill Evening Star: Letters to the Editor, Sep 1949-Oct 1949 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Peekskill Joint Veterans Committee: Correspondence, Aug 1949 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - People's Artists, 1949-1972 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Progressive Party, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Radosh, Ronald: "The Anti-Communist Intellectuals in the 1950's" (typescript), undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Research: General, 1925-1981 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Research: Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Research: Stock Footage and Stills, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Research Notebooks (I), undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Research Notebooks (II), undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Research Notebooks: Beinecke, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Research Notebooks: Civil Rights Congress, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Research Notebooks: Schomburg, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Research Notebooks: Typed, undated (Box 4, Folder 30a)
  - Reuss, Richard: “The Peekskill Riots: Domestic Cold War in Action!” (seminar paper), 1962-1980 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Robeson, Paul: Biographical Information, 1949-1979, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Rogge, O. John, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Schlosser, Anatol I.: "Paul Robeson: His Career in the Theatre, in Motion Pictures, and on the Concert Stage" (Ph. D. dissertation, NYU, pp 1-418), 1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Schultz, Rabbi Benjamin, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sharrow, Victor, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Stark, Leo, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Straus, Leon: FBI File, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Subversive Activities Control Act (S. 2311, 81st Congress), 1949 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Summer Camps and Colonies, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Szego, Stephen, 1949, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - United States Civil Service Commission: Loyalty Review Board, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Westchester County Police Departments: Reports, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Westchester County Sheriff’s Office: Bus Companies Report (notes), 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Westchester County Sheriff’s Office: Bus Drivers Interviews, Oct 1949 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Westchester County Sheriff’s Office: Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Westchester County Sheriff’s Office: Reports, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Westchester County Sheriff’s Office: Report to Governor Thomas E. Dewey, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Westchester County Veterans of Foreign Wars, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Who Is Who in Peekskill(photocopy), 1954 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - WLNA Highland Broadcasting Corporation: Radio Bulletins, Aug 1949-Sep 1949 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Yeakey, Lamont H.: "Paul Robeson: His Early Nationalist Years" (conference paper), 1971 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Series IV: Artifacts and Oversize Ephemera, 1936-1949.
  - Civil Rights Congress Newsletter: "Stop the Anti-Negro Terror" (flyer, Aug 30, 1949), National Ad Hoc Committee to End the Crimes against Paul Robeson: A Statement of Conscience, re: Paul Robeson (play, undated), undated, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Croton Consumers Club Directory (Mar 1936), Skyway Service Stations Receipt (Aug 21, 1949), 1936, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Maps, undated (Box 6, Folder 2a)
  - New York State Police: Material Picked Up at Scene, Riot #1 (Blank Cashier’s Checks, Signage), 1949 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Signs from Concert, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)